<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Enhancers on Roger Mulet</title>
    <link>https://rmulet.github.io/tags/enhancers.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Enhancers on Roger Mulet</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rmulet.github.io/tags/enhancers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>From Genotype to Phenotype: How Enhancers Control Gene Expression and Cell Identity in Hematopoiesis</title>
      <link>https://rmulet.github.io/publications/reviewenhancers2023.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rmulet.github.io/publications/reviewenhancers2023.html</guid>
      <description>Blood comprises a wide array of specialized cells, all of which share the same genetic information and ultimately derive from the same precursor, the hematopoietic stem cell (HSC). This diversity of phenotypes is underpinned by unique transcriptional programs gradually acquired in the process known as hematopoiesis. Spatiotemporal regulation of gene expression depends on many factors, but critical among them are enhancers—sequences of DNA that bind transcription factors and increase transcription of genes under their control.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title> Induced cell-autonomous neutropenia systemically perturbs hematopoiesis in Cebpa enhancer-null mice </title>
      <link>https://rmulet.github.io/publications/bloodadvances2022.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rmulet.github.io/publications/bloodadvances2022.html</guid>
      <description>The transcription factor C/EBPa initiates the neutrophil gene expression program in the bone marrow (BM). Knockouts of the Cebpa gene or its +37kb enhancer in mice show 2 major findings: (1) neutropenia in BM and blood; (2) decrease in long-term hematopoietic stem cell (LT-HSC) numbers. Whether the latter finding is cell-autonomous (intrinsic) to the LT-HSCs or an extrinsic event exerted on the stem cell compartment remained an open question. Flow cytometric analysis of the Cebpa +37kb enhancer knockout model revealed that the reduction in LT-HSC numbers observed was proportional to the degree of neutropenia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The leukemic oncogene EVI1 hijacks a MYC super-enhancer by CTCF-facilitated loops</title>
      <link>https://rmulet.github.io/publications/ctcf.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rmulet.github.io/publications/ctcf.html</guid>
      <description>Acute myeloid leukemia (AML) with inv(3)/t(3;3)(q21q26) is a distinct World Health Organization recognized entity, characterized by its aggressive course and poor prognosis. In this subtype of AML, the translocation of a GATA2 enhancer (3q21) to MECOM (3q26) results in overexpression of the MECOM isoform EVI1 and monoallelic expression of GATA2 from the unaffected allele. The full-length MECOM transcript, MDS1-EVI1, is not expressed as the result of the 3q26 rearrangement. Besides the classical inv(3)/t(3;3), a number of other 3q26/MECOM rearrangements with poor treatment response have been reported in AML.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atypical 3q26/MECOM rearrangements genocopy inv(3)/t(3;3) in acute myeloid leukemia </title>
      <link>https://rmulet.github.io/publications/atypical3q26.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rmulet.github.io/publications/atypical3q26.html</guid>
      <description>Acute myeloid leukemia (AML) with inv(3)/t(3;3)(q21q26) is a distinct World Health Organization recognized entity, characterized by its aggressive course and poor prognosis. In this subtype of AML, the translocation of a GATA2 enhancer (3q21) to MECOM (3q26) results in overexpression of the MECOM isoform EVI1 and monoallelic expression of GATA2 from the unaffected allele. The full-length MECOM transcript, MDS1-EVI1, is not expressed as the result of the 3q26 rearrangement. Besides the classical inv(3)/t(3;3), a number of other 3q26/MECOM rearrangements with poor treatment response have been reported in AML.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
